

F. Paul Spitzher

Franz Paul Spitzner

Somewhere down the line of my studies I realized that I love to code and to tinker with tech—sometimes more than doing the actual research. I also love to write texts that are easy to get and to create figures that make people understand all the crazy things we scientists came up with.

What's it all about if not for making science accessible to everyone?

PERSONAL INFORMATION



Address

MPIDS Am Faßberg 17 37077 Göttingen



Date of birth

December 23 1990



Email

paul.spitzner@ds.mpg.de

HOBBIES AND PASSION



Cycling



Photography



Webdesign



Clean code



Open source software

OUTREACH



Website https://makeitso.one



GitHub pSpitzner



LinkedIn pSpitzner

EDUCATION

Dr. rer. nat. · Göttingen University

2023 Physics of biological and complex systems

Thesis: Spreading processes in complex networks

of cultured neurons and society

Grade: summa cum laude

Master of science · Leipzig University

2017 International physics studies program

Thesis: Two perspectives on the condensation-evaporation transition

of the Lennard-Jones gas in 2D

Bachelor of science · Leipzig University

2015 International physics studies program

Thesis: Generating long-range power-law correlated disorder

RESEARCH EXPERIENCE

Max Planck Institute for Dynamics and Self-Organization

2018-2023 · PhD student, Priesemann group

Developed an open-source Python toolbox (*Mr. Estimator*) Modeled neuronal cultures using numeric simulations Studied human contact networks and disease spread

University of Barcelona

2019 · Laboratory rotation, Soriano lab

Designed and performed experiments on neuronal cultures *in vitro*

Leipzig University

2017–2018 • Research assistant, CQT group
Studied finite-size scaling of equilibrium phase transitions

Leibniz Institute for Tropospheric Research

2015–2017 · Research assistant, part time

Developed an atmospheric model using OpenCL, running on GPUs and heterogeneous computing environments

CHARACTER

Self-motivated

Openminded

Organized

Solution-oriented

<u>So</u>ft skills

Attention to detail

Critical thinking

Teamwork

Leadership

COMMUNICATION

Figures and design

Conflict resolution Scientific writing

Presentations

Posters

LANGUAGES

German native

English fluent

Spanish intermediate

PROGRAMMING, SOFTWARE AND TOOLS

Python C++ OpenCL JavaScript Bootstrap PHP HTML, CSS Bash
SSH
Git
CI/CD
Unit testing

Docker compose

Virtualization macOS Linux HPC

Kanban PARA Serif Affinity Suite Final Cut Pro Blender

LaTeX Markdown Apple/MS Office

RESEARCH LINKS





arXiv

TRAINING AND DEVELOPMENT

Attended workshops and conferences on computational physics, neuroscience and scientific writing

Organized and lead conference workshops and group retreats

Lead seminars on illustration, scientific writing and productivity tools

Supervised students for their theses

Worked in internships and part-time jobs involving sales, programming, product design and project management

Former board member in a voluntary association organizing student venues

SELECTED PUBLICATIONS

Yamamoto* et al. 2023 · Science Advances

Modular architecture facilitates noise-driven control of synchrony in neuronal networks

Zierenberg* et al. 2023 · New J. Phys.

How contact patterns destabilize and modulate epidemic outbreaks

Neto* et al. 2022 · Plos CB

Sampling effects and measurement overlap can bias the inference of neuronal avalanches

Spitzner et al. 2021 · Plos ONE

Mr. Estimator, a toolbox to determine intrinsic timescales from subsampled spiking activity

Dehning* et al. 2020 · Science

Inferring change points in the spread of COVID-19 reveals the effectiveness of interventions

REFERENCES



Somme Som

^{*} equal contribution